Climate change is already a heavy topic,
قد تحدث الكثيرون عن التغير المناخي
and it's getting heavier
وهو أمرٌ يزداد أهمية كل يوم
because we're understanding
لانني نعي
that we need to do more than we are.
أننا يتوجب ان نفعل أكثر مما نقوم به الآن مع هذه المشكلة
We're understanding, in fact,
لقد تبين لنا ..
that those of us who live in the developed world
انه يجب على من يعيش من العالم المتقدم
need to be really pushing towards eliminating our emissions.
ان يدفع بخياراته لكي يصل الى انعدام انبعاثات الكربون
That's, to put it mildly, not what's on the table now.
وهذا لكي نكون واقعيين ليس ما هو موجود على طاولة الحوار اليوم
And it tends to feel a little overwhelming
ولكننا اليوم مغلوب على أمرنا
when we look at what is there in reality today
فعندما ننظر الى ما يجري على ارض الواقع
and the magnitude of the problem that we face.
فإننا نعي الحجم الكبير للمشكلة التي نواجهها
And when we have overwhelming problems in front of us,
وعندما نواجه مشكلات عويصة جداً
we tend to seek simple answers.
فنحن نحاول البحث عن الاجوبة السهلة
And I think this is what we've done with climate change.
واعتقد ان هذه هي سياسة الحل اليوم امام معضلة التغير المناخي
We look at where the emissions are coming from --
فنحن ننظر الى المكان الذي تظهر منه الانبعاثات
they're coming out of our tailpipes and smokestacks and so forth,
فنقول ان السيارات و مداخن المصانع ..
and we say, okay, well the problem is
ونحو ذلك هي المشكلة
that they're coming out of fossil fuels that we're burning,
والتي تعتمد في الاساس على الوقود الاحفوري الذي يحرق من اجل جلب الطاقة
so therefore, the answer must be
لذا وعلى ما سبق فإن حل تلك المشكلة - التغير المناخي -
to replace those fossil fuels with clean sources of energy.
هو لابد تغير الوقود الاحفوري بمصدر نظيف من الطاقة
And while, of course, we do need clean energy,
وبينما فعلاً نحن بحاجة لاستبدال الوقود الاحفوري بوقود نظيف
I would put to you that it's possible
اريد أن انوه انه وبالدفع في اتجاه
that by looking at climate change
ان التغير المناخي هو مشكلة
as a clean energy generation problem,
حلها استبدال الوقود الاحفوري
we're in fact setting ourselves up
فاننا نضع انفسنا في مكان
not to solve it.
يجعل من الاستحالة حل مشكلة التغير المناخي
And the reason why
وسبب ذلك منطقي ..
is that we live on a planet
وهو اننا نعيش على كوكب
that is rapidly urbanizing.
يتمدن بصورة سريعة جداً
That shouldn't be news to any of us.
وهذا امرٌ ليس بالجديد لنا
However, it's hard sometimes
ولكن احيانا نحن لا نعي حجم ذلك الامر ..
to remember the extent of that urbanization.
ومدى امتداد التمدن الجاري في هذا العالم
By mid-century,
ففي منتصف القرن القادم
we're going to have about eight billion -- perhaps more -- people
سنغدو ما يقارب 8 مليارات نسمة
living in cities or within a day's travel of one.
تعيش في مدن تبتعد عن بعضها البعض مسافة سير يوم واحد فقط
We will be an overwhelmingly urban species.
سوف نصبح متمدنين جدا
In order to provide
و من اجل ان نتمكن من توفير
the kind of energy that it would take
الطاقة اللازمة لهذا التمدن
for eight billion people living in cities
الذي يحوي 8 مليارات شخص
that are even somewhat like the cities
والتي سيكون استهلاكها من الطاقة
that those of us in the global North live in today,
يشابه تلك المدن التي تقع في الجزء الشمالي من الكرة الارضية
we would have to generate
سيكون علينا
an absolutely astonishing amount of energy.
ان نولد كمية هائلة من الطاقة
It may be possible
ومن الممكن
that we are not even able
ان لا نكون قادرين على
to build that much clean energy.
بناء مولدات طاقة نظيفة تستطيع استيعاب هذا الطلب
So if we're seriously talking about tackling climate change
لذا ان كنا فعلا راغبين في ايقاف مشكلة التغير المناخي
on an urbanizing planet,
على كوكبنا المتمدن هذا
we need to look somewhere else for the solution.
علينا ان ننظر الى نوعية حلول أخرى
The solution, in fact, may be closer to hand than we think,
ان الحل ربما يكون اقرب الينا مما نعتقد
because all of those cities we're building
لان كل المدن التي نعمل على انشائها
are opportunities.
تملك في طياتها فرصاً لذلك الحل
Every city determines to a very large extent
فكل مدينة تعمد الى توسيع كم الاستهلاك من الطاقة
the amount of energy used by its inhabitants.
لمواطنيها الى الحد الاقصى
We tend to think of energy use as a behavioral thing --
ونحن نعمل على ان ننظر الى الطاقة " كسلوك "
I choose to turn this light switch on --
فأنا على سبيل المثال " أختار أن أشعل الاضواء = سلوك "
but really, enormous amounts of our energy use
ولكن في الحقيقة استهلاك الطاقة " الكم الكبير منها "
are predestined
هو امرٌ محتوم ..
by the kinds of communities and cities that we live in.
بسبب نوعية المجتمعات والمدن التي نعيش بها
I won't show you very many graphs today,
لن أريكم الكثير من الاستبيانات اليوم
but if I can just focus on this one for a moment,
ولكن أريدكم أن تنظروا الى واحدة فقط
it really tells us a lot of what we need to know --
انها تخبرنا الكثير عما نحتاجه اليوم ..
which is, quite simply,
فبعض الحلول بسيطة جداً ..
that if you look, for example, at transportation,
فإن نظرنا على سبيل المثال الى المواصلات
a major category of climate emissions,
والتي هي عنصر اساسي من عناصر الانبعاثات الغازية المؤدية الى التغير المناخي
there is a direct relationship
فهناك علاقة مباشرة
between how dense a city is
بين الكثافة السكانية في المدن
and the amount of climate emissions
وبين كم الانبعاثات التي تصدرها تلك المدن
that its residents spew out into the air.
جراء استخدامات مواطنيها
And the correlation, of course,
والعلاقة هي .. طبعاً
is that denser places tend to have lower emissions --
انه كلما كانت المدينة اكثر كثافة .. كلما كان انبعاث الغازات منها اقل
which isn't really all that difficult to figure out, if you think about it.
وهو أمرٌ ليس صعب الفهم ان فكرنا به جيداً
Basically,
فنحن في الاساس
we substitute, in our lives,
على الدوام في احتياج لبعض المستهلكات
access to the things we want.
ونحتاج الوصول اليها
We go out there and we hop in our cars
فما يحدث هو اننا نستخدم السيارات
and we drive from place to place.
ومن ثم نقود سياراتنا من مكان الى مكان
And we're basically using mobility to get the access we need.
فنحن نتجول لكي نصل الى حاجياتنا
But when we live in a denser community,
ولكن عندما نعيش في مجتمع ذا كثافة مرتفعة
suddenly what we find, of course,
فاننا نجد على الدوام
is that the things we need are close by.
ان الاشياء التي نحتاجها موجودة بالقرب منا
And since the most sustainable trip
ولان " الانتقال المستدام = الانتقال بإنبعاث غازات منخفض "
is the one that you never had to make in the first place,
هو تنقل لم تكن قد قمت به من قبل بسبب بعد المسافة
suddenly our lives become instantly more sustainable.
اصبح فجأة هو الاكثر ترجيحاً و اصبحت تنقلاتنا مستدامة أكثر
And it is possible, of course,
واعتقد انه من الممكن حتماً
to increase the density of the communities around us.
زيادة كثافة المجتمعات من حولنا
Some places are doing this with new eco districts,
فبعض المدن تعمل على بناء مقاطعات صحية ..
developing whole new sustainable neighborhoods,
حيث تقوم ببناء أحياء كاملة مستقلة مستدامة
which is nice work if you can get it,
انه عمل مميز ان استطعنا القيام به
but most of the time, what we're talking about is, in fact,
في معظم الاحيان ما نتحدث عنه ..
reweaving the urban fabric that we already have.
هو إعادة توظيف توزيع نسيج المدن الذي نملكه
So we're talking about things like infill development:
نحن نتحدث عن أشياء من مثل تطوير أنظمة رمي المخلفات
really sharp little changes
انها تغيرات بسيطة جداً
to where we have buildings, where we're developing.
يمكننا ان نطبقها على المباني ... في المناطق نطورها
Urban retrofitting:
نحن يجب ان نتحرك نحو التعديل المحدث للتمدن
creating different sorts of spaces and uses
بحيث نستغل كل اشكال المساحات والمناطق
out of places that are already there.
الغير مستغلة الموجودة في المدن
Increasingly, we're realizing
ونحن اليوم وبصورة متزايدة
that we don't even need to densify an entire city.
ندرك اننا لسنا بحاجة الى ان مدن كاملة بكثافة مرتفعة جداً
What we need instead is an average density
انما ما نحتاجه كثافة متوسطة
that rises to a level
ترتفع الى مستوى معين
where we don't drive as much and so on.
بحيث لا يتوجب علينا ان نقود سياراتنا لمسافات طويلة
And that can be done
وهذا يمكن القيام به
by raising the density in very specific spots a whole lot.
عن طريق رفع الكثافة في " نقاط مركزية " الى حد كبير
So you can think of it as tent poles
يمكن تشبيه تلك النقاط بأعمدة الخيام
that actually raise the density of the entire city.
والتي تكون ذا كثافة كبيرة جداً اكثر من المدينة وتمثل نواة لها
And we find that when we do that,
وقد وجدنا عندما نقوم بهذا ..
we can, in fact, have a few places that are really hyper-dense
يمكننا ان نركز بشدة في مناطق مركزية في المدينة
within a wider fabric of places
بحيث تغطي مساحة عريضة من حولها
that are perhaps a little more comfortable
وهذا أكثر سلاسلة و خيار مريح اكثر للبناء والسكان
and achieve the same results.
ويحقق نفس النتائج المرجوة
Now we may find that there are places that are really, really dense
الآن يمكن أن يكون هناك مدنٍ كثيرة الكثافة ..
and still hold onto their cars,
ولكن أفرادها مازالوا متمسكين بسياراتهم
but the reality is that, by and large,
ولكن الواقع هو ما قلته .. الانبعاثات ستقل
what we see when we get a lot of people together with the right conditions
فما يحدث عندما نضع الناس ضمن ظروف ملائمة وصحيحة
is a threshold effect,
هو تغير حقيقي
where people simply stop driving as much,
بحيث سوف يقل استخدام السيارات
and increasingly, more and more people,
وبصورة متزايدة على الدوام
if they're surrounded by places that make them feel at home,
لان الناس محاطة بأماكن تشعرها بالاكتفاء و أماكن تشعرها بحميمة المنزل
give up their cars altogether.
مما يجعلهم يستغنون عن التنقلات البعيدة .. والتوقف عن الاكثار من استخدام السيارات
And this is a huge, huge energy savings,
وهذا توفير كبير في استخدامات الطاقة
because what comes out of our tailpipe
لان ما يخرج من عوادم السيارات
is really just the beginning of the story
هو فعلاً ذا تأثير كبير على القضية ..
with climate emissions from cars.
قضية التغير المناخي
We have the manufacture of the car, the disposal of the car,
فجميعاً يُصنع من أجله السيارات .. وتُهلك من أجله
all of the parking and freeways and so on.
كما ان السيارات لها عدة ملحقات مضرة بالبيئة مثل مواقف السيارات والطرق السريعة
When you can get rid of all of those
ان استطعنا ان نتخلى عن كل هذا
because somebody doesn't use any of them really,
بسبب امتناعنا عن استخدام السيارات
you find that you can actually cut transportation emissions
سوف نرى ان الانبعاثات المضرة بالبيئة
as much as 90 percent.
سوف تنخفض الى نحو 90%
And people are embracing this.
والناس سوف يقدرون هذا ..
All around the world, we're seeing more and more people embrace this walkshed life.
ونحن نرى في انحاء العالم كيف ان الكثير من الاشخاص بدأوا يقدرون حياة " السير "
People are saying that it's moving from the idea of the dream home
وهذه اليوم تعبر بحسب قول البعض عن الانتقال من الحصول على " بيت الاحلام "
to the dream neighborhood.
الى الحصول على " حي الأحلام "
And when you layer that over
وعندما ننشر هذا الامر
with the kind of ubiquitous communications that we're starting to see,
وبوجود هذا الكم من التقدم في الاتصالات
what you find is, in fact,
سنجد انه بمقدورنا
even more access suffused into spaces.
ان نتواصل بدون المواصلات عبر الكثير من الطرق
Some of it's transportation access.
ويمكننا ان نصل الى حيث ما نريد بكل سهولة
This is a Mapnificent map that shows me, in this case,
هذه هي خريطة مصغرة توضح لي
how far I can get from my home in 30 minutes
الاماكن التي يمكن ان اصلها من منزلي خلال 30 دقيقة
using public transportation.
باستخدام المواصلات العامة
Some of it is about walking. It's not all perfect yet.
وبعض تلك الاماكن يمكن ان اذهب اليها سيراً على الاقدام
This is Google Walking Maps.
وهذه هي خريطة جوجل للسير
I asked how to do the greater Ridgeway,
وعندما طلبت منه الذهاب الى Ridgeway
and it told me to go via Guernsey.
قال لي انه يتوجب الذهاب عبر Guernsey
It did tell me that this route
ولكنه نوه لي الى
maybe missing sidewalks or pedestrian paths, though.
ان ذلك الطريق ربما لا يحوي في اجزاءه على مسارات خاصة للمشاة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the technologies are getting better,
ان التكنولوجيات تتقدم .. ومازالت قاصرة
and we're starting to really kind of crowdsource this navigation.
ولكننا ننتقل اليوم الى كم من الاشخاص يريدون فعلاً ذلك " استخدام المشي " و التوجه بواسطته
And as we just heard earlier,
وقد سمعنا من قليل في محادثة سابقة
of course, we're also learning how to put information on dumb objects.
كيف يمكننا ان نضع المعلومات على العناصر الصلبة
Things that don't have any wiring in them at all,
دون ان نصلها باي اسلاك او نحو ذلك
we're learning how to include
لذا نحن ننتقل الى مرحلة
in these systems of notation and navigation.
يمكننا ان نحيط أنفسنا بواسائل التوجيه والتحديد
Part of what we're finding with this
وبعض ما نكتشفه خلال ابحاثنا
is that what we thought
ان ما نظنه انه
was the major point
النقطة الاساسية في الحل
of manufacturing and consumption,
خلال التصنيع والاستهلاك
which is to get a bunch of stuff,
والذي يشمل العديد من النطاقات
is not, in fact,
هو في الحقيقة ليس كذلك
how we really live best in dense environments.
فطريقة عيشنا في المدن ذات الكثافة المرتفعة هو الامر الأعم
What we're finding is that what we want
ماوجدناه اننا بحاجة الى استخدام أمثل
is access to the capacities of things.
للمعدات والادوات على سبيل المثال
My favorite example is a drill. Who here owns a drill, a home power drill?
ومثالي المفضل لتوضيح هذه الفكرة هو "الثاقب" .. من يملك منكم ثاقباً في المنزل .. ثاقب كهربائي ..
Okay. I do too.
حسناً انا أملك ..
The average home power drill is used somewhere between six and 20 minutes
اتعلمون أن معدل استخدام الثاقب الكهربائي على مدى كامل استخدامه
in its entire lifetime,
هو بين 6-20 دقيقة فقط
depending on who you ask.
بحسب الشخص المعني
And so what we do is we buy these drills
ان ما يحدث هو اننا نشتري هذه الثواقب
that have a potential capacity of thousands of hours of drill time,
والتي إنتاجيتها تقارب آلاف الساعات من الثقب
use them once or twice to put a hole in the wall and let them sit.
ولا نستخدمها الا مرة أو مرتين ومن ثم نركنها على الرفوف
Our cities, I would put to you,
ومدننا هي كذلك في هذه الحالة
are stockpiles of these surplus capacities.
هناك الكثير من " الانتاجيات المهدورة "
And while we could try and figure out
وعلينا ان نكتشف ونولد طرقاً جديدة
new ways to use those capacities --
لاستهلاك تلك الانتاجيات المهدورة\الغير مستخدمة
such as cooking or making ice sculptures
مثل الطبخ .. او صناعة مجسمات الثلج
or even a mafia hit --
او ربما هجوم عدائي ..
what we probably will find
ما سوف نجده جراء ذلك ..
is that, in fact, turning those products into services
ان استخدام تلك الادوات الكثيرة الموجودة من حولنا
that we have access to when we want them,
واستغلال انتاجياتها المهدورة
is a far smarter way to go.
هي طريقة ذكية جداً للمضي قدماً في مشروعنا ضد التغير المناخي
And in fact, even space itself is turning into a service.
وحتى المساحات اليوم قد تحولت " الى خدمات "
We're finding that people can share the same spaces,
كما نرى يمكن للاشخاص ان يستخدموا المساحات المشتركة
do stuff with vacant space.
والمساحات الغير مستغلة
Buildings are becoming bundles of services.
فقد غدت المباني اليوم منظومات متكاملة من الخدمات
So we have new designs
لدينا اليوم تصاميم جديدة
that are helping us take mechanical things that we used to spend energy on --
تساعدنا في استغلال الحركات الميكانيكية و استغلال الطاقة
like heating, cooling etc. --
مثل التسخين والتبريد
and turn them into things that we avoid spending energy on.
لكي نحولها الى وسائل تقلل من هدرنا للطاقة
So we light our buildings with daylight.
فيمكننا ان نضيء المباني بضوء الشمس
We cool them with breezes. We heat them with sunshine.
ويمكننا ان نقوم بتبريدها بواسطة تيارات الهواء .. وتدفئتها بواسطة اشعة الشمس
In fact, when we use all these things,
في الحقيقة عندما نقوم بكل هذا
what we've found is that, in some cases,
فاننا في بعض الحالات التي درسناها
energy use in a building can drop as much as 90 percent.
وجدنا ان استهلاك الطاقة قد انخفض 90%
Which brings on another threshold effect
مما يعيدنا الى نقطتي الاولى .. وهي التاثير الكبير الذي تحدثت عنه من الحلول الصغيرة
I like to call furnace dumping,
والتي اسميها " التخلي عن الأفران "
which is, quite simply,
وهو بكل بساطة
if you have a building that doesn't need to be heated with a furnace,
ان استطعنا أن نحصل على مبنى لا يحتاج أن يتم تدفئته بواسطة الأفران
you save a whole bunch of money up front.
فأنت سوف توفر الكثير من الكلفة
These things actually become cheaper to build
وهذه الامور هي أقل كلفة من بناء
than the alternatives.
البدائل النظيفة
Now when we look at being able
فنحن عندما نصل الى طرق تمكننا من
to slash our product use, slash our transportation use,
" مضاعفة " استخدام انتاجية منتجاتنا .. ووسائل نقلنا
slash our building energy use,
وطاقة المباني المحيطة بنا
all of that is great, but it still leaves something behind.
كل هذا رائع .. ولكننا مازلنا متأخرين على هذا الطريق
And if we're going to really, truly become sustainable cities,
وان اردنا حقاً ان نغدو مدناً مستدامة
we need to think a little differently.
علينا فعلاً ان نغير من طريقة تفكرينا
This is one way to do it.
وما ذكرت سابقاً هي إحدى الطرق
This is Vancouver's propaganda about how green a city they are.
هذا إعلان لمدينة فانكوفر .. يوضح عن طريقهم نحو المدن الخضراء
And certainly lots of people have taken to heart
والكثير من الاشخاص اعتقدوا ان هذه الفكرة
this idea that a sustainable city is covered in greenery.
تعني ان المدن المستدامة هي تلك التي يكسوها غطاء أخضر
So we have visions like this.
نحن لدينا هذا التصور
We have visions like this. We have visions like this.
كهذه .. وهذه .
Now all of these are fine projects,
وهذه مشاريع رائعة حقاً
but they really have missed an essential point,
ولكنها تفتقد الى النقطة الاساسية
which is it's not about the leaves above,
والتي هي ان المشكلة ليست في المساحات الخضراء التي تعلو المدينة
it's about the systems below.
بل في الانظمة الموجودة أسفلها
Do they, for instance, capture rainwater
فهل هذه المشاريع تستهدف على سبيل المثال .. استغلال مياه الامطار
so that we can reduce water use?
هل تقلل استخدام المياه بصورة عامة
Water is energy intensive.
ان المياه هي طاقة كامنة
Do they, perhaps, include green infrastructure,
هل تتضمن تلك الحلول بنى تحتية خضراء
so that we can take runoff
هل تستخدم التيار المائي
and water that's going out of our houses
الذي يخرج من منازلنا ومبانينا
and clean it and filter it
وتقوم بتنظيفه وفلترته
and grow urban street trees?
ومن ثم استخدامه في ري المزروعات في المدن
Do they connect us back to the ecosystems around us
هل تقوم بعمل إتصال بيننا وبين الانظمة الحيوية من حلونا
by, for example, connecting us to rivers
اي على سبيل المثال .. ان تعيد اتصالنا مع الانهار
and allowing for restoration?
او تساعد على استعادة الكائنات الحيوية
Do they allow for pollination,
هل تلك الحلول لا تؤذي عمليات التلقيح
pollinator pathways
ولا تعترض هجرة الملقحات
that bees and butterflies and such can come back into our cities?
التي تسلكها النحل و الفراشات .. هل تسمح تلك الحلول بعودة الملقحات تلك ؟
Do they even take the very waste matter
هل تأخذ بعين الاعتبار الهدر ..
that we have from food and fiber and so forth,
الذي يحدث في الاطعمة والالبسة ونحو ذلك
and turn it back into soil
وإعادتها الى التربة
and sequester carbon --
هل تستخدم أحجار الكربون
take carbon out of the air
والتي تمتص الكربون من الهواء
in the process of using our cities?
لتنظيف مدننا
I would submit to you that all of these things are not only possible,
انا لا اقول لكم ان كل ما ذكرته هو أمرٌ ممكن ..
they're being done right now,
بل هو حقيقي ويحدث في عدة مدن من حولنا
and that it's a darn good thing.
وهو شيء رائع حقاً
Because right now, our economy by and large
وأريد ان اختم بقولي ان اقتصادنا الكبير اليوم
operates as Paul Hawken said,
يتحرك بموجب قول " بول هواكين " عبر مبدأ
"by stealing the future, selling it in the present
"السرقة من المستقبل والبيع في الحاضر
and calling it GDP."
بوصف ذلك بالناتج المحلي الإجمالي"
And if we have another eight billion
وان كان هناك اليوم 8 مليارات
or seven billion,
او 7 مليارات
or six billion, even, people,
او 6 مليارات نسمة اضافيين
living on a planet where their cities also steal the future,
تقوم بذات الامر .. وتعيش في المدن التي تسرق من المستقبل
we're going to run out of future really fast.
فإننا سوف لا محالة نفقد ذلك المستقبل في القريب العاجل وبسرعة كبيرة جداً
But if we think differently,
ولكن ان استطعنا ان نفكر بصورة مغايرة
I think that, in fact, we can have cities
اعتقد اننا سنصل ذات يوم بصورة جدية
that are not only zero emissions,
ليس فقط الى مدن تحوي انبعاثات غازات ضارة معدوم
but have unlimited possibilities as well.
بل الى خيارات جديدة غير محدودة
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)